[Music]
i've addressed how cell phones may
affect brain function and how both cell
phones and wi-fi may affect male
fertility but what about the effects of
wi-fi on brain functioning the possible
existence of cognitive effects of these
kinds of radio frequency energies has
been one of the more contentious
discussions in the forever contentious
issue of whether exposure has any health
consequences whatsoever
wi-fi has been called an uncontrolled
global experiment on the health of
humankind the effects of radio frequency
fields gained new urgency as the world
health organization officially declared
cell phone radiation to be a possible
human carcinogen based on brain tumor
risks
but their decision has no direct
relevance to the possible health effects
of wi-fi since the exposures are so much
different we may absorb 100 times less
radiation in a typical exposure to wi-fi
compared to cell phones
but you don't know if there are effects
until you put it to the test
can wi-fi affect brain function to date
more than 100 studies have been
published on the effects of these kinds
of emissions on human brainwave patterns
as measured by eeg
while the results are mixed a fairly
consistent finding is that even a short
duration of exposure to the head can
produce small but statistically
significant changes in the eeg of
resting and sleeping subjects this
effect is acknowledged by most health
agencies but the question is
what do you do with that information for
example a review sponsored by the
european governing body concluded that
the relevance of such small changes
remains unclear and we don't even know
how it's happening at all
some have suggested it's an artifact of
the test and that eeg wires may be
acting like antennas that carry the wave
straight to the brain in effect
contributing to the changes that's it's
been set up to measure
either way you don't see the kind of
neural cognitive effects with wi-fi
exposure that you do with cell phones
for example no measurable effects were
found on reaction time or sustained
attention now this was testing 2.4
gigahertz wi-fi but if anything we would
expect even lower levels of exposure
from the newer five gigahertz wi-fi due
to the shallower penetration depth
though more accurately a person who
spends hours a day glued to a smartphone
or tablet may very well experience all
sorts of neurocognitive effects
but from the use of this technology not
from the radiation
it's interesting there's a large
literature out there about the health
implications of these new technologies
for young people but it's about the
content
for example never before in history has
such sexually explicit material been
indiscriminately available to youth and
we need to ask ourselves as a society
what effect this may be having girls and
boys are being exposed to a colossal
amount of digital media on smartphones
which makes access to pornographic
material all too easy cheap and
anonymous
no longer confined to homes and bedrooms
young people can now watch pornography
in school on public just a touch of a
button away and researchers only begun
cataloging the effects this may have on
young people's attitudes and behaviors
most college students these days report
seeing online pornography as a minor
before age 18 of 1500 high school boys
surveyed the vast majority admit to
accessing web porn nearly one and three
for more than an hour at a time
what is that teaching our next
generation of men researchers sat
through and content coded 400 videos
from mainstream internet porn sites and
more than a third of the videos
displayed acts of physical violence
against women such as gagging or choking
yeah but does watching such material
lead to sexually aggressive behaviors
fifteen hundred ten to fifteen-year-olds
were followed for years to see the if
there was a link between intentional
exposure to such material and later
sexually aggressive behaviors such as
sexual assault they found that exposure
to violent porn over time predicted an
almost six-fold increase in the odds of
self-reported sexual aggression
the question of course though is which
came first right a major difficulty with
interpreting this kind of research is
you know that teens predisposed to that
kind of behavior of course the ones who
may be drawn to that material in the
first place so no cause and effect link
can be established
all we can do as parents is closely
monitor what our children are doing to
the best of our abilities
[Music]
foreign